Guide to the George F. Warren papers, 1892-1938.
Warren, George F. papers, 1892-1938
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
George F. Warren papers, 1892-1938.
21-10-77
George F. (George Frederick) Warren, 1874-1938.
18.5 cubic ft.,
Papers, correspondence, diaries, theses, articles, maps, surveys, reports, pamphlets, clippings, photogrpahs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Materials pertaining to Warren's work in agricultural economics, both as a professor at Cornell and as a public policy advisor.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of agricultural economics and farm management at Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers of George F. Warren include correspondence, theses, and articles by Warren and others; and maps, surveys, census materials, lecture notes, speeches, reports, pamphlets, clippings, photographs, and other materials pertaining to Warren's work in agricultural economics, both as a professor at Cornell and as a public policy advisor. Specific topics include agriculture lectures at Cornell, the United States economy and agricultural policies, Warren's activities as economic advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt during his presidency, the gold standard for U.S. currency, the War Food Administration (1917-1919), New York State Food Supply Commission (dealing primarily with milk supply), Warren's trips to Europe in 1924 for the Tariff Commission, the International Conferences on Agricultural Economics (1929, 1933, 1936), the Committee for the Nation to Rebuild Prices and Purchasing Power (1933-1935), the New York State Planning Board (1934-1935), and related subjects. Also, a series of "diaries" compiled by Warren to document his activities, which include correspondence, memos, reports, drafts, photographs, printed material, and notes; a bound volume of correspondence (1928-1939) regarding "Interrelationships of Supply and Price," a bulletin written by Warren and Frank A. Pearson; and a volume of "Speeches on Prices." Original manuscript for Prices by Warren and Frank Pearson (3 vols.). And 20 household accounts (1906-1931). Annotated nineteenth edition of Elements of Agriculture with edits for the subsequent edition.
Also, original personal letters written to George Warren, with a volume of typed transcripts by Ruth Warren Gerlach: "Letters from Home Written to George Frederick Warren (1874-1938) from 1892 to 1911"; and family photographs. Correspondence with Irving Fisher and James Harvey Rogers. Chapters from a book on Harley and Verda Warren, George Warren's nephew.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Warren, George F. 1874-1938.; Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947.; Pearson, Frank A. (Frank Ashmore), 1887-; Rogers, James Harvey, 1886-1939.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Cornell University--Faculty.; New York State Food Supply Commission.; New York State Planning Board.; United States. Committee for the Nation to Rebuild Prices and Purchasing Power.; United States. War Food Administration.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Economic aspects.; Economic policy.; Gold standard.; Milk supply--New York (State); Agriculture--Accounting.; Agricultural economists.
Places:
United States--Economic policy.
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Maps.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Surveys.; Account books.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Jean Warren oral history, #47-2-O.H.70
CONTAINER LIST
- 1900-1911 (Box 1)
- 1900-1911 Correspondence (Box 2)
- 1912-1916 (Box 3)
- War Food Administration, 1917 (Box 4)
- War Food Administration, 1917 (no. 2) (Box 5)
- War Food Administration, 1917 (no. 3) (Box 6)
- War Food Administration, 1917 (no. 4) (Box 7)
- War Food Administration, 1917 (no. 5) (Box 8)
- 1920-1921 (Box 9)
- 1922-1924 (Box 10)
- 1924 Denmark (Box 11)
- 1925-1927 (Box 12)
- 1928-1930 (Box 13)
- 1931-1933 (Box 14)
- 1933 (Box 15)
- 1934 (Box 16)
- 1934-1935New York State Planning Board (Box 17)
- 1934-1935New York State Planning Board (no. 2) (Box 18)
- 1935-1936 (Box 19)
- 1937-1938 and updated; 1909-1930 Census Material (Box 20)
- Pamphlets and Published Material (Box 21)
- Contents Not Described (Box 22)
- Contents Not Described (Box 23)
- Photographs (Box 24)
- Account Book, 1892-1897 (Box 25, Folder 1)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, 1897-1900 (Box 25, Folder 2)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, 1901 (Box 25, Folder 3)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, 1902 (Box 25, Folder 4)
- Agriculture Lectures C.U., 1902-1903 (Box 25, Folder 5)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, 1903-1904 (Box 25, Folder 6)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, 1905 (Box 25, Folder 7)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, 1906 (Box 25, Folder 8)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, 1907; 1911 (Box 25, Folder 9)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, 1913 (Box 25, Folder 10)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, 1914 (Box 25, Folder 11)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, 1915 (Box 25, Folder 12)
- Pamphlets, Maps, Guides, 1915 (Box 25, Folder 13)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, 1916 (Box 25, Folder 14)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, 1916 (Box 25, Folder 15)
- Chapters on Oats, Barley, Rye, and Flax, 1916 (Box 25, Folder 16)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1917-July 1917 (Box 25, Folder 17)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, August 1917-December 1917 (Box 25, Folder 18)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1918-February 1918 (Box 25, Folder 19)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, March 1918-April 1918 (Box 25, Folder 20)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, May 1918-September 1918 (Box 25, Folder 21)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, October 1918-December 1918 (Box 25, Folder 22)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1919-April 1919 (Box 25, Folder 23)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, May 1919-September 1919 (Box 25, Folder 24)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, November 1919-December 1919 (Box 25, Folder 25)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1920-March 1920 (Box 25, Folder 26)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, April 1920-May 1920 (Box 25, Folder 27)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, June 1920-August 1920 (Box 25, Folder 28)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, September 1920-December 1920 (Box 25, Folder 29)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1921-March 1921 (Box 26, Folder 1)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, April 1921-May 1921 (Box 26, Folder 2)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, June 1921-July 1921 (Box 26, Folder 3)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, July 1921-August 1921 (Box 26, Folder 4)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, September 1921-October 1921 (Box 26, Folder 5)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, September 1921-December 1921 (Box 26, Folder 6)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, November 1921-December 1921 (Box 26, Folder 7)
- Dr. Warren in Europe, September 1921-February 1922 (Box 26, Folder 8)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1922-February 1922 (Box 26, Folder 9)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, February 1922 (Box 26, Folder 10)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, March 1922-October 1922 (Box 26, Folder 11)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, April 1922-July 1922 (Box 26, Folder 12)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, November 1922-December 1922 (Box 26, Folder 13)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1923-February 1923 (Box 26, Folder 14)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, March 1923-April 1923 (Box 26, Folder 15)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, May 1923-July 1923 (Box 26, Folder 16)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, August 1923-September 1923 (Box 26, Folder 17)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, October 1923-December 1923 (Box 26, Folder 18)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1924-May 1924 (Box 26, Folder 19)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, June 1924-October 1924 (Box 26, Folder 20)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, November 1924-December 1924 (Box 26, Folder 21)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1925 (Box 26, Folder 22)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, February 1925-April 1925 (Box 26, Folder 23)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, May 1925-July 1925 (Box 26, Folder 24)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, August 1925-October 1925 (Box 26, Folder 25)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, November 1925-December 1925 (Box 26, Folder 26)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1926-February 1926 (Box 26, Folder 27)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, March 1926-September 1926 (Box 26, Folder 28)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, October 1926-December 1926 (Box 26, Folder 29)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1927-February 1927 (Box 26, Folder 30)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, March 1927-August 1927 (Box 26, Folder 31)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, September 1927-December 1927 (Box 26, Folder 32)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1928 (Box 27, Folder 1)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, February 1928-April 1928 (Box 27, Folder 2)
- Statement by Lloyd S. Tenny to Senate, April 26, 1928 (Box 27, Folder 3)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1928-June 1928 (Box 27, Folder 4)
- German Conferences, May 1928-October 1928 (Box 27, Folder 5-11)
- German Conferences, June 1928-August 1928 (Box 27, Folder 12-13)
- German Conferences, June 1928-September 1928 (Box 27, Folder 14)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, July 1928-August 1928 (Box 27, Folder 15)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, July 1928-September 1928 (Box 27, Folder 16)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, October 1928-December 1928 (Box 27, Folder 17)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1929-February 1929 (Box 27, Folder 18)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, March 1929-May 1929 (Box 27, Folder 19)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, June 1929-July 1929 (Box 27, Folder 20)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, August 1929-October 1929 (Box 27, Folder 21)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, November 1929-December 1929 (Box 27, Folder 22)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1930 (Box 27, Folder 23-24)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany (Farmer's Week), February 1930 (Box 27, Folder 25)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, February 17, 1930-March 1930 (Box 27, Folder 26)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, May 1930-August 1930 (Box 27, Folder 27)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, September 1930-August 1930 (Box 27, Folder 28)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, November 1930-December 1930 (Box 27, Folder 29)
- "Economic Outlook for Agriculture in the U.S.", December 10, 1930 (Box 27, Folder 30)
- "Economic Outlook for Agriculture in the U.S.", December 10, 1930 (Box 27, Folder 31)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1931-March 1931 (Box 27, Folder 32)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, April 1931-June 1931 (Box 27, Folder 33)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, July 1931-October 1931 (Box 27, Folder 34)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, November 1931-December 1931 (Box 28, Folder 1)
- Public Problems of Agriculture, Term II Lectures and Assignments, 1931-1932 (Box 28, Folder 2-4)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1932 (Box 28, Folder 5)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, February 1932 (Box 28, Folder 6)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, March 1932 (Box 28, Folder 7)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, April 1932-May 1932 (Box 28, Folder 8)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, June 1932 (Box 28, Folder 9)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, July 1932 (Box 28, Folder 10)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, Aug. 1932 (Box 28, Folder 11)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, September 1932 (Box 28, Folder 12)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, October 1932-November 1932 (Box 28, Folder 13)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, December 1932 (Box 28, Folder 14)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1933 (Box 28, Folder 15)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, February 1933-March 1, 1933 (Box 28, Folder 16)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, March 27, 1933 (Box 28, Folder 17)
- The New York Times, March 12, 1933 (Box 28, Folder 18)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, April 1-10, 1933 (Box 28, Folder 19)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, April 11-29, 1933 (Box 28, Folder 20)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, May 1933-June 1933 (Box 28, Folder 21)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, July 1933-August 1933 (Box 28, Folder 22)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, September 1933 (Box 28, Folder 23)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, October 1933 (Box 28, Folder 24-26)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, November 1933 (Box 28, Folder 27)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, December 1933 (Box 28, Folder 28)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1934 (Box 28, Folder 29)
- Hearings: Gold Reserve Act of 1934, January 19-23, 1934 (Box 28, Folder 30)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, February 1934 (Box 29, Folder 1)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, March 1934 (Box 29, Folder 2)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, April 1934 (Box 29, Folder 3)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, May 1934 (Box 29, Folder 4)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, June 1934-July 1934 (Box 29, Folder 5)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, August 1934 (Box 29, Folder 6)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, September 1934 (Box 29, Folder 7)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, September 1934-October 1934 (Box 29, Folder 8)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, November 1934 (Box 29, Folder 9)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, December 1934 (Box 29, Folder 10)
- Notes on "Continent", 1934 (Box 29, Folder 11)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1935 (Box 29, Folder 12)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1935-February 1935 (Box 29, Folder 13)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1935-1935 (Box 29, Folder 14)
- U.S. Senate Hearings, January 1935-February 1935 (Box 29, Folder 15)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, March 1935 (Box 29, Folder 16)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, March 1935-June 1935 (Box 29, Folder 17)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, July 1935-August 1935 (Box 29, Folder 18)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, October 1935 (Box 29, Folder 19)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, November 1935-December 1935 (Box 29, Folder 20)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1936-February 1936 (Box 29, Folder 21)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1936-February 1936 (Box 29, Folder 22)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, March 1936-June 1936 (Box 29, Folder 23)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, July 1936-September 1936 (Box 29, Folder 24)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, October 1936-December 1936 (Box 29, Folder 25)
- Land Classification Maps, 1936 (Box 29, Folder 26)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1937-April 1937 (Box 29, Folder 27)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, May 1937-June 1937 (Box 29, Folder 28)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, July 1937-December 1937 (Box 29, Folder 29)
- "Diaries" and Miscellany, January 1, 1937-June 31, 1937 (Box 29, Folder 30)
- "Agricultural Survey of Caledonia, Avon, York, Geneseo, Lima, Livingston County, New York", n.d. (Box 29, Folder 31)
- "Geographical, Economic, and Social Condition of Agriculture in the U.S." (Box 29, Folder 32)
- Papers by Warren, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 33)
- Papers by Warren and Others (Box 29, Folder 34)
- Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 35)
- Photographs, 1920; n.d. (Box 29, Folder 36)
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 37)
- Bound volume of correspondence concerning "Interelationships of Supply and Price," a bulletin written by Warren and Frank A. Pearson, 1928-1932 (Box 30)
- Minden, Nebraska Newspapers, 1902-1903 (Box 31, Folder 1)
- Printed Materials on Ithaca's Alken Farm, 1919 (Box 31, Folder 2)
- The Price-Campbell Cotton Picker Corporation in Dallas, Texas, 1911 (Box 31)
- A Blueprint Map of the Taft Ranch (Corpus Christie Bay), 1912 (Box 31)
- "Elements of Agriculture", by George Warren, 1921 (Box 31)
  Annotated throughout by Warren and with some original photos used for illustrations.
- George and Mary Warren account book of personal expenditures, 1917 (Box 31)
- "Speeches on Prices," 1 bd. vol. (Box 32)
- The Mechanical Analysis of Soils, C.U. Bachelor of Sciences thesis, 1903 (Box 33)
- A Soil Survey of the Cornell University Farms, C.U. Master of Science thesis, 1904 (Box 33)
- Annotated copy of Farm Management by GFW, New York: The MacMillan Company, 1913 (Box 33)
- History of Warren Home Land (Box 33, Folder 1)
- Development of Farm Business Charts, 1926-1972 (Box 33, Folder 2)
- 1 Volume of miscellaneous speeches on economic conditions, February 1932-December 1937 (Box 34)
- 1 Volume of Miscellaneous speeches agriculture in New York State, December 1923-October 1936 (Box 34)
- 1 Volume of miscellaneous speeches on the currency question, May 1932-February 1936 (Box 34)
- Prices of Farm Products in New York, 1923 (Box 34)
  Original typewritten manuscript of N.Y. Agricultural Experiment Station Bulletin 416
- Prices 1932 (Box 34)
  Original typewritten manuscript by G. F. Warren and F. A. Pearson. In 3 volumes
- Journal of Warren's farm operation giving pay for family labor, inventories of fall plowing, etc., 1 bound vol., 1916-1920 (Box 35)
- Account Books, 15 bound and 16 unbound volumes for Warren's household and farm operation, 1906-1929 (Box 36)
- Journals, 4 large bound vols. of Warren's household and farm, 1901-1934 (Box 37)
- Bound volume Letters from Home. Includes letters written to George Frederick Warren from 1892 to 1911 compiled by Ruth Warren Gerlach, May 2003. (Box 38)
- Personal correspondence, 1892-1901 (Box 39)
- Personal correspondence, 1901-1906 (Box 40)
- Personal correspondence, 1906-1911 (Box 41)
- Correspondence between Warren and James Harvey Rogers (Yale economist) and Irving Fisher, 1874-1938 (Reel 1)
- Warren diary and correspondence (Reel 2)
- Publications by Warren, 1906-1937 (Box 42)
- Chapters from a book by Larry Olson on Harley and Verda Warren, 2002 (Box 42)
- Group panorama photograph of a conference, 1936 (Mapcase-folder 1)